I want to stick on this just for a
second because you're talking about the
societal impact and the breakdown that
we have from this.
And while that's all happening and while
that's all true and while it's
uh worse than most people have paid
attention to and realized, at the same
time,
we have the salt in the wound of seeing
the fraud that's coming out of Minnesota
and the fraud that's coming out of
California. And the reason why that's
salt in the wound is to your point,
double income families who don't even
get a chance to enjoy themselves, right?
There's none left for themselves. They
don't even get to see their kids, are
barely scraping by, and then you have
illegal immigrants that are making
millions, tens of millions, or billions
of dollars fraudulently. And And And the
worst part is
the single biggest expense that's
causing the double incomes to fall
behind is health care and day care. And
that's where all the fraud is happening.
So, how does that start to add up with
this?
Now, think about it from the perspective
You do everything right. You do
everything that you've been told to do.
You work hard, you know, you You work
long hours just to try to get ahead, and
then there's no jobs. I mean, you have
no You know, you know, the chances of
advancing in your career are just They
diminish all the time. So, you're
struggling really hard, doing everything
right, doing everything that you're
supposed to do, and you can barely make
ends meet. You can barely scrape by. You
know, there's not a whole lot to look
forward to because the future looks
bleaker and bleaker and bleaker, as you
said, Bart. And it just gets worse and
worse and worse. And then,
who is the one Who are the ones who are
getting ahead in this economy? It's the
people who are perpetuating fraud and
doing everything wrong, or at least
everything that you've told are supposed
to be wrong. And not only are they doing
something wrong, it appears as though at
least some segments of the population
are just winking and nodding, approving
of it. Not just approving of it, at
least letting it happen. Yeah. It is not
just a slap in the face. It is a
dangerous breakdown of, you know,
some some parts of the social contract
contract and the political contract, and
it is absolutely dangerous, especially
given these economic circumstances and
situation. You can't have the vast
majority of people doing the right
things and struggling and getting
further and further behind and then
reward people for doing, you know, basic
fraud. And let's also be clear, too. All
of this fraud is really coming from what
happens when governments go insane. I
mean, you have to expect in 2021, 2022,
2020, 2021, governments went absolutely
insane. Government expenditures
increased through the roof and in many
ways this type of behavior was
encouraged by the government. In fact,
it was a stimulus program of the
government. You know, the PPP loans,
wink and a nod there. The PPP loans were
essentially a way, "Hey, just take our
money so that the economy doesn't
collapse." And so that just fed into
more and more of the same same type of
behavior. It becomes sort of It becomes
almost normalized. So, on the one hand,
you're pissing off the regular regular
people who are doing everything right.
On the other hand, in just pure economic
terms, you're encouraging the most
unproductive, inefficient, and just
downright immoral behavior possible.
Again, it's another angle in which the
economy is going to only struggle to
grow because it can't overcome that
degree of inefficiency, rigidity, and
just plain stupidity. And it's just the
tension just ratchets up further and
further the longer this goes on. The
more people are aware of what's what's
taking place, it just You're right, it's
pouring It's not just pouring a couple
of grains of salt in the wound, it's
dumping bucketloads of it in people's
wounds. Specific Yes, and just
specifically that is worth repeating.
The two biggest areas where people
struggle are health care and child care.
And that's where all the fraud Like, if
all that fraud wasn't there, the health
care and child care probably wouldn't be
so expensive. And so it's like it's even
worse. Um I saw in California, I think
it was over the last four or five years,
the population grew by 2%
but the but the amount of government
workers went up by 25%
and the amount of spending went up by
48%.
Like
and [clears throat] that's and that's
where the fraud comes from, right?
Because once you open up the tabs, it's
it's almost like license to steal. Um
it's it's it's just become We've known
this from the beginning of time. People
have been talking about this forever. Um
you know, hard money proponents, you
don't give government the opportunity
because as soon as you do, what happens?
Government will do exactly what we'd
expect it to do, which is be corruptive.
It corrupts not only people, it corrupts
the entire system that it tries to
operate in. Yeah.
>> So, when we expanded, we When we
expanded, we collectively allowed the
government to expand in '21 and 2022.
Again, another
you know, absolutely shameful uh outcome
from the pandemic and the lockdowns.
When the government expanded, it opened
the door. They just didn't open the door
a little crack, it opened the door, you
know, wide open for all this kind of
behavior. Um so, then we shouldn't be
surprised when these are the outcomes
because it's it's the one goes One that
follows the other. Yeah.
Now, um you know, we have all that and
it's not just the fraud, obviously.
That's like
I hope it's the straw that breaks the
camel's back. Um but, you know, Elon
Musk and Doge uncovered all types of
fraud as well as waste. Um and then that
got shut down pretty quickly. And you
can you can see pretty quickly that
there's no appetite for reducing
expenses. The question I want to ask
though is um if we were able to
meaningfully cut expenses, some of these
cuts that Doge had uncovered, or this
fraud, could that be detrimental to the
economy?
Maybe in the short run because you cut
off the money, but I, you know, long
run, it's only positive. One of the
things that we need to do to get
economic growth back on track. And this
goes back to 2008. Uh one of the biggest
problems with 2000 There was a lot of
problems with 2008, but one of the
problems was that the government
responded to 2008. Um you know,
Keynesian stimulus all over the economy.
And it's been a it's been a enlarging
Keynesian stimulus uh parade ever since
then. Not just in the US, but all over
the world. The Chinese are the the
poster child Yeah.
>> for Keynesian stimulus. It just gets
bigger and bigger and bigger. And the
more the the
the bigger the government gets, um, just
like following along with the Japanese
did from 1990 on through, more the worse
the economy performs, the more stimulus
you get from the government. The
government gets bigger, the worse the
economy performs, which justifies even
more government. And you never get out
of this rut. We we followed the same
path right down to I mean, from QE on
down. Uh, we went to the same exact
tactics because economists are all
basically the same thing. So, from 2008
forward,
the government got bigger and bigger. It
started with TARP under Bush, and then
it got the ARRA under Obama. And it
never went down. Even the first Trump
administration, as you said, Mark, the
DOE thing last year didn't really make
much of a dent. Government gets bigger
and bigger and bigger, and the economy
gets worse and worse and worse. Those
two things are indeed correlated because
one does help cause the other. So, one
of the ways we need to get out of this
economic rut is to cut back on the
government, and probably cut back a
severe amount. So, maybe there is a
short-run They call it a recession if
you want. A government cut back
recession, which would be worth it for
the short-run pain because if we trim
the government relative to the size of
the economy, it will allow some parts of
the economy that we need to flourish to
start flourishing and doing all of the
things the productive things that we
needed to do to create a sustainable
economic recovery in advance. Right. The
more the government, you know,
interferes, the more fraud there is, the
more waste there is, uh, the more
inefficient an economy becomes, which
means it diminishes not just the
short-run, but the long-run potential.
That's really the thing. It's the
long-run potential that's been harmed
for for way too long. And the only
answers we're ever given is, well, we
just need more government. The next
stimulus will fix it. We'll get it
bigger and bigger and bigger, and the
next one will do it. And it it never
does.
Would say that sort of the financial
world, maybe the the models that you
look through, historical parallels, the
data you look through, changed in 2008?
And what I mean by that is when you look
back to previous recessions, previous to
2008, it seemed like the Fed and the
government allowed the bubble to sort of
deleverage. And so we saw the markets
crash, and then we kind of got through
that.
In 2008, it seemed like they tried to
allow to deleverage, and then as you
said, they threw in the tarp and and
they just they they launched QE. Once
they launched QE, the system got so
leveraged up, 2018, 19, Powell tried to
let it deleverage, couldn't let it let
it happen. Uh in 2020, we leveraged up
even more. 2023, the banks three banks
collapsed within 6 days, a bailout was
put together. And it seems like now,
from 2008 forward, the leverage Two
things have happened. The leverage has
been built up so much from QE
ongoing, but also the appetite for
allowing the system to deleverage at all
has gone away. And it seems like
anything from 2008 forward is in a
different sort of reality. Would you
Would you agree with that? I absolutely
agree with that, but for different
reasons. I look at it it's somewhat the
opposite of you do, Mark. And that's the
data shows that we
we the system deleveraged. Uh the
government didn't want it to. That's
exactly what the bailouts were. And so
the bailouts were counterproductive in
the sense that they they
they kept afloat the wrong businesses.
Um they kept afloat the businesses that
were impaired, and therefore were never
actually going to contribute to growth.
So yes, the whole point of deleveraging
is that you get rid of the bad stuff, so
some good stuff can grow in its place.
But we did deleverage. And it we
deleveraged in 2008 dramatically. In
fact, it went way too far. That was the
That's the other part of this problem.
Um the banking sector never recovered
from 2008. I know it seems like um
that's not the case, but you look at any
of the statistics, you know, it's it was
a unit root. You know, uh bank bank
assets were going in a trend like this.
You hit the 2008 and then the trend
changes. It's still growing, but it's
growing at nowhere near the same rate as
it did before 2008.
So, there's a definitely a trend change
and a deleveraging that the system
forced on itself. And in that
deleveraging, what happened? The banking
sector and the financial sector as a
whole prioritized safety and liquidity.
This is depression economics. You saw
the same thing in the 1930s. Um
The prioritizing safety and liquidity,
sadly, the system treats government debt
as the safest and most liquid. It's most
liquid because it's the deepest market
for those instruments, but it's
perceived to be safe
for historical reasons.
But in preferencing the safest and most
liquid assets under depression economics
meant that governments realized, they
figured out relatively soon,
because the system wants safe and liquid
instruments, governments could give them
as many safe and liquid instruments as
they possibly wanted. So, governments no
longer had any constraint. This is the
death of bond vigilantism. The reason
why bond vigilantism is nowhere to be
seen is because of depression economics.
So, banking banks, hedge funds, basis
traders, all of it. They they they went
nuts for government debt at the expense
of more productive riskier debt like
loans into the real economy.
So,
it fed into both of those negative
probably have too much deleveraging on
the one side in the banking sector, but
that deleveraging that preferenced the
governments to get bigger and bigger and
bigger. It gave them an out it gave them
an an open road to get bigger and bigger
and bigger and to interrupt um
and to overtake and what's the what's
the term? Crowd out
private credit opportunities. Let's talk
about private credit opportunity.
Uh I want to talk about um maybe the
Fed's
Some people want to say binary out
options that they have in front of them
and they have a changing Fed chair next
month. Uh but before we get to that, you
had said at the beginning, well, you
just said private credit. Uh you said in
the beginning you said can I give you A
and B and so A was the oil price, B was
private credit.
And so um there's a big problem with
private credit. Some of the big private
credit firms have uh
held back redemptions, things like that.
Um some people are saying this could be
a massive uh deal. I think Jamie Diamond
said uh when you see a couple
cockroaches, that means there's more
cockroaches.
What is going on with private credit and
is it a big danger? You said it's the
second most thing uh most important
thing you're paying attention to.
>> Well, that's the argument. There there's
no longer an argument that there's a
problem there. I mean even J. Powell at
Harvard the other day said, "Yeah,
there's going to be some losses."
And so that's where it really starts. Uh
it's never losses that turn something
bad or something like a credit bust into
a credit crisis. It's not the losses
that do it. It's the psychology
surrounding it. And it's the same thing
we just talked about in the real economy
just in the financial context. Uh
private credit providers, which I mean
shadow banks are nothing more than the
Wall Street's answer to what I just
talked about, the deleveraging among the
regulated banking system. Wall Street
stepped in with these you know, these
vehicles, these investment funds to do
lending that Wall Street banks weren't
doing and because Wall Street banks were
um lending to the to the federal
government. So I mean in the 2010s you
saw a rise of non-bank shadow banks,
whatever term you want to use. The Fed
calls them non-depository financial
institutions, whatever. So these funds,
these banks, these shadow banks started
to rise in the 2010s and that was fine.
But then everything went crazy when
again during the pandemic and the
lockdowns in the early 2020s. Um because
a lot of people I mean it's easy to to
fool yourself and convince yourself that
so you know, the good times are going to
last forever,
these private credit providers just went
absolutely crazy. First of all, they had
access to funds, they had access to
money, so they were looking for
opportunities to deploy it. And since
everybody said in 2021, this is going to
be red hot for the foreseeable future,
they just started shoveling it out there
in the real economy. The thing is
though, when you got to 2022 and 2023,
when things started to change, the
private credit suppliers by then, they
were making way too much money to shut
it down or even even slow it down. They
kept shoveling even more money. In fact,
they actually went even more crazy the
farther the Fed hiked short-term
interest rates, which is one reason why
you end up with bubbles to begin with.
Um rate hikes actually create bubbles,
not rate cuts.
Um
so the private credit providers just
went crazy at a time they should have
been cutting back. They should have It
was very similar to subprime mortgages.
This is why you hear people talking
about the 2008 parallels. This is very
similar. Um loss rates were very low,
and this is tends to happen in every
bubble period. Loss rates are very low,
and then all of a sudden they shoot up
higher. But when loss rates are low year
after year after year, as they were in
subprime mortgages, um in 2004-2005,
loss rates in subprime mortgages were in
small single digits for years on end. So
what happens? You convince yourself
there's no risk. You convince yourself
that there's no downside, so you can do
any kind of risky behavior that you
want. Plus, there's some, you know, new
finan- new fancy financial engineering
available that, you know, you can even
further fool yourself that there's no
risk. And so what happens is everybody
reaches for yield, everybody gets in on
the party, and pretty soon you lose
sight of any kind of fundamental
grounding or basis, and you just start
doing more and more stupid You
start lending to people you never would
have lent to if you had a sane head, you
know, a sane perspective. So that all
happened. We all know what happened. In
fact, you know, what did Jeffrey
Gundlach uh called it last fall, you
know, garbage lending. We all know there
was tons of garbage lending over the
last couple years. And now that garbage
lending is going to produce some degree
of losses. So what we're trying to
figure out now is who's going to end up
taking the losses, how much are they
going to end up taking the losses, and
what are those losses going to do to the
rest of the system such that the system
will be able to absorb them. What really
happened in 2008 was that expectations
were way misaligned with reality, and in
recalibrating expectations,
you turn what would have been a
relatively small affair in subprime
mortgages into a complete systemic crash
because there was no way There's not
enough information. There was no way to
to to really assign those losses in a
way that people were would be would
would maintain their trust and faith and
confidence in the system. It's really
about confidence and behavior, which
determines the issue here. So, what
we're struggling with is we know that
there's a lot of stupid garbage lending
in private credit. We know the size and
scale of private credit is pretty
substantial. It's not subprime or really
mortgages. It's not the same scale of
2008. It's fortunately significantly
less than that. However, it is big
enough where if we do end up turning a
credit bust into a crisis, it could
definitely damage, lead to financial
volatility. It could further damage the
real economy because once you shut off
when you turn a private credit bubble
into a bust, one thing that happens is
the credit stops flowing, and then
everything downstream of these shadow
banks ends up getting getting deprived
of credit, which means they can't stay
afloat. They start laying off workers,
and there's macroeconomic effects from a
credit crunch that builds up. And so,
the question is how big is this private
credit thing? How big of a reaction will
it have across the entire marketplace?
And what inevitably will be the cost to
the real economy? That's what we're
struggling to find out now. Now,
we know that there's a private credit
bust taking place. We just don't know
how much of an impact it will have. I
tend to be a little bit more
pessimistic, be surprised, than most
people because um
the scale is sufficient, and I don't
think the system is all that strong and
resilient to begin with. And And um I
think we've seen evidence of that more
recently. And we're just starting to see
more and more uh signs of this
really beginning to escalate. A couple
big ones, not just uh the the the
outflows from hedge funds more recently.
I mean, the Blue Owl ones are pretty
stunning. Uh when you have 40% of a
hedge fund
investors want 40% of their money back
out of the entire fund, that's a shadow
bank run. And we've seen multiples of
those take place, but the real big one
is when the banking sector says, "I'm
not going to fund this anymore." And we
saw that happen to a small degree a
couple weeks ago when JP Morgan started
to revalue collateral. What they're
really saying is, "We're looking at
different ways that we can protect
ourselves from the potential fallout
should this private credit thing really
start to really start to kick off." And
if more and more banks behave the same
way, then it turns off the bank money
from these shadow banks and it forces
them to start selling assets, and that's
where you really get into the major
trouble. And why does anybody care? Not
anybody. Why would the average investor
care? Why would the average investor
care about this? Um is it because
they've used their pension money to go
into these and they could take a acute
loss there? Is it because of the
volatility that it could create across
the market? Like why would the average
investor, boomer, retiree, something
think about this? Yeah, because there's
a tight correlation between risk taking
and things like private credits and just
credit overall and the willingness of
investors to take risk in things like
assets or things like stocks and
equities. So, if you have a private
credit bust, immediately people start
selling, and that selling is going to
spill over into the stock market. Uh so,
if you if this this continues to go in
the same way, stock prices are going to
go lower. They won't have the ability to
withstand um
a real substantial setback in the credit
markets. And then there's the
macroeconomic consequences.
Uh macroeconomic consequences that you
know, same thing for for uh
for asset classes as the real economy.
When you have macroeconomic
consequences, people don't want to take
risks. I mean, the one the one
macroeconomic scenario that always
produces major losses in equities is a
recession. So, if you have a credit
crunch that is big enough that it turns
off the um the credits credit flow to
some of these struggling businesses and
they have to start laying off workers
and produces a recession scenario,
especially when combined with an energy
shock, which is why it was 1A and 1B,
you get an energy shock plus a credit
crunch that develops. Well, suddenly,
you know, the chances of unemployment
really spiking here,
and that produces the one thing that
that stock market always does poorly in.
The one scenario, the one circumstance
stock market always does poorly in. But,
it's not it's not just the financial
consequences. I think the bigger bigger
problem is the
Like I said, the real macro economic
consequence, cuz we can't really afford
more unemployment.
Most people have already been
impoverished to begin with, and now
you're going to take away some of their
jobs, too.
That really pushes things too far, or at
least it risks pushing things too far.
You think that Maybe there's sort of two
ways through this. So, like, number one
would be more like a 2008 style event
where
it blows up, it creates contagion,
it's acute, and government, the Fed, is
forced to intervene and interact and put
money back in the system.
That may be the more favorable approach.
The other approach might be more like a
Japan 20-year sort of wallow through
this, where it's like it blows up a
little bit, and then it kind of gets
resolved, and then another one blows up,
and it creates like decades of
volatility that starts to wash people
out. That's where we are already, and so
I think there's a good chance that's the
actual scenario. In fact, I call it the
worst-case scenario. Because time is the
bigger and component here. It would be
much better, far better, if we have a
complete collapse of the system
tomorrow. As painful as that would be if
we had another 2008
>> style. Yeah, if we had another 2008
tomorrow, but then we responded to it in
a sane, legitimate way that allowed it
for an actual recovery to take place on
the other side, that would be far more
preferable than to have a very slow,
minimal kind of, as you said, a little
bit of volatility here and there, where
you just kind of plod along. It's never
really going to take off, but it never
really gets that bad to begin with.
Nobody can really figure out what's
wrong because just it seems like
something's missing but you can't really
put your finger on it. That is by far
the worst case scenario and that's the
one we've been following since 2008. We
have no economic growth to speak of. I
mean you look at all the charts and the
trend change in 2008. So if we have
another private credit bust, that raises
the chances of being stuck in the same
paradigm for even longer. Which to me is
by far the worst case. I would much
prefer to have a 2008 crash reset a
potential um everything going again than
to just sit here and be stuck in the
same kind of uh Well, you said you said
>> nowhere. You said we've been stuck in
that the worst case scenario. We've been
stuck in that volatility crab walk
sideways whatever since 2008.
We haven't had any growth. But when I
look at markets, I mean markets are up,
S&P 500's up, Nasdaq's up, uh real
estate's up. So it looks like there's
plenty of growth in that. Are you You're
saying no meaningful growth in GDP
but asset prices are up.
No, I look at the participation rate of
the labor
>> have made a lot of money. Investors have
made a lot of money but you got to
remember that most of those investments
have nothing to do with the
macroeconomic fundamentals. Our stock
market is has nothing to do with the
economy. Um earnings nothing to do with
stock prices. That's the fair fiction
and fairy tale that everybody tells
themselves. But it's really nothing more
than you buy stocks because other people
buy stocks and so what you're really
trying to do is figure out when other
people might buy stocks so that you can
buy stocks ahead of them. You put this
um this sort of legitimate gloss on it
so it sounds like it's it's a you know a
relatively scientific process but it's
really not. It's a casino. And when more
and more people play the casino and this
by the way is why you should listen to
Mike Green. Um Mike Green he talked
about passive investment which really
explains uh the signal you get from the
stock market is nothing more than more
people are saving in the retirement
through stocks. So the more people who
save in the retirement, the money goes
right into the stock market regardless
of what's taking place in the
fundamentals of the real economy. So,
asset prices are divorced from economic
fundamentals, which produces the
situation where this if you think the
stock market is sending you a signal
about the condition in you know,
whatever the real economy, labor market,
whatever, and stock markets are up here,
but unemployment is down here, you are
first of all very confused, but it also
feeds into this dynamic where people are
looking for other situation because if
you think the stock market is
representing the economy and it's
booming, but you don't see any boom
anywhere, nobody's hiring people are
laying off, it leads to you know, this
political dissolution where people look
for more extreme more extreme
answers to questions they don't really
know how to ask. So, yeah, you look at
any economic statistics in any country
in the world well, almost any country in
the world. There are certain exceptions.
2008,
GDP didn't just fall off, it changed
trend. It was growing at a rate for 60
years, and then 2008 it stopped growing
at the same rate. It fell off sharply
and it never recovered. And because
there wasn't enough output, there wasn't
enough employment. So, participation in
the overall labor market fell off
sharply and it never recovered. We
ratcheted lower and lower and lower.
There are fewer people working, which
leads to social consequences. Why was
there such an epidemic of heroin
overdoses and deaths and suicide
throughout the 2010s into the 2020s?
Because economic opportunity all but
disappeared at the margins and those
margins got bigger and bigger and
bigger. Yeah. So, the economy it overall
just completely changed. In 2008 it has
never gone back. So, in the 2020s
to suffer something like a private
credit crisis would only further risk
doing more of the same even further into
time.